A Guide to the Frances Leigh Williams Papers, 1935-1977
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Frances Leigh Williams Papers, 1935-1977
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 20
4.8 linear feet
Frances Leigh Williams
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The original collection was donated to the Department by Miss WIlliams in May 1969. The collection was augmented in May 1980 by Mollie Holt the executrix of Miss Williams' estate.
Biographical/Historical Information
Frances Leigh Williams (1909-1978) was born in Richmond on March 20, 1909, the daughter of Francis Deane and Mary Mason Williams. She was a cousin of the Virginia novelist Ellen Glasgow.
After graduation from St. Timothy's in 1926, she attended Smith College for a year. On leaving college, she accepted a position with the Richmond News Leader as a reporter and columnist. In 1935, she left the News Leader to become a research assistant for Douglas Southall Freeman. She worked with him on the biographies of Robert E. Lee and George Washington. During this period, she wrote and published Historic Richmond: Her Story and Her Spirit. In 1951, she wrote They Faced the Future, a brief history of the State-Planters Bank of Richmond.
In 1949, Williams had become, with her partner Winifred Hanigan, co-owner and executive manager of the Sea Horse Hotel in Virginia Beach, Virginia. This career led directly to her first book for young people entitled Welcome to Dunecrest, published in 1955. This was followed by The Shawnee Trail in 1958, a book based on an historic tale of Indian capture in late 18th century Virginia. Williams noted that this was the story Ellen Glasgow wanted her to tell. In 1863, Rutgers University Press published her celebrated Matthew Fontaine Maury: Scientist of the Sea. Her biography of the noted Naval Scientist was well-received and won acitation from the United Daughters of the Confederacy. Four more historical works followed the biography of Maury: A Century of Service(1965); Ocean Pathfinder(1966); Plantation Patriot(1967); and A Founding Family: The Pinckneys of South Carolina(1978). Williams was well-known for an abiding interest in history, particularly Virginia history, and she was a popular after-dinner speaker for a number of organizations. She died in 1978.
Scope and Content Information
The Papers of Frances Leigh Williams includes Miss Williams' major published works, in manuscript and proof form, as well as letters from Ellen Glasgow and Carl Van Vechten.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as it was donated. Oversize material can be found in Drawer 27.
Contents List
- Biographical information and book reviews 1948-1972 (Box 1)
- Drafts of speeches given by Frances Leigh Williams 1961-1975 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous articles written by FLW 1934-1950 (Box 1)
- Article by Douglas Southall Freeman in the Carnegie Magazine1935 (Box 1)
- Letters Ellen Glasgow and Carl Van Vechten 1935-1942 (Box 1)
- Lay-out and draft: Introduction Matthew Fontaine Maury, n.d. (Box 1)
- Matthew Fontaine Maury, n.d., TMs, p. 1-300 (Box 1)
- Matthew Fontaine Maury, n.d., TMs, p. 1-652 (Box 2)
- Bibliography: Matthew Fontaine Maury, n.d., p. 336-406 (Box 3)
- Galley proofs: MFM, Introduction 1963, 26 pages (Box 3)
- Index Cards: MFM (Box 3)
- Lay-out and draft: Photo-section: MFM, n.d. (Box 3)
- Photo-section (Blues): MFM1963 (Box 3)
- Page proofs Ocean Pathfinder(Inc. jacket cover) 1966 (Box 3)
- Plantation Patriot 1967, TMs (Box 4)
- Lay out and page proofs of Plantation Patriot1967 (Box 4)
- Notes and carbon They Faced the Future (Box 4)
- Frances Leigh Williams by Rebecca Y. Williams, n.d., TMs, AMs (Box 4)
- The Shawnee Tomahawk, n.d., TMs (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous materials re: The Shawnee Tomahawk, n.d. (Box 5)
- Welcome to Duncrest, n.d., TMs (carbon) (Box 5)
- Research material and miscellaneous material Welcome to Duncrest, n.d. (Box 5)
- A Founding Family: The Pinckneys of South Carolina 1977, TMs (Box 5)
- A Founding Family: The Pinckneys of South Carolina 1977, TMs (Box 6)
- Index cards: A Founding Family1977 (Box 7)
- Guide to the Museum of Early Southern Decorative Arts 1977 (Box 7)
- Oversize Materials (Oversize 27)